Guide to the Margaret Fishback Papers, 1863-1978 and undated RL.00397
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Margaret Fishback papers
1863-1978 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Fishback, Margaret, 1904-1985
RL.00397
52 Linear Feet
Margaret Fishback was an advertising copywriter for Macy's, Cecil & Presbrey, Warwick & Legler, Young & Rubicam, Doyle Dane Bernbach, and a number of freelance clients. A poet, columnist, and author of prose work, she contributed frequently to national magazines and published several books. The Margaret Fishback Papers span the years 1863 through 1978 and document Fishback's dual careers in advertising and writing as well as her personal life. The collection includes correspondence, layouts, drafts, galley proofs, radio scripts, working copy of advertising text, poetry, prose, published material, appointment books, scrapbooks, photographs, and other materials. Clients represented in the papers include Borden's, Chef Boy-Ar-Dee, Clairol, General Foods, Gourmet Foods, Gimbels, Macy's, Martex, Moore-McCormack Lines, Norcross, Norsk, Pabst, and Simmons Beautyrest.
About 35,700 items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Margaret Fishback Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift from Anthony Antolini in 2005.
Biographical Note
Margaret Fishback
1900 Mar. 10 Born Margaret Fishback, Washington, D.C.
1917 Graduated from Central High School (Washington, D.C.)
1921 A.B. degree, Goucher College (Baltimore, Md.)
1921 Teacher, English and History, Columbia Junior High School (Washington, D.C.)
1922 Organizational Department, Tamblyn and Brown (New York, N.Y.)
1926-1930 Divisional copywriter, R. H Macy & Co. (Macy's)
1930-1942 Institutional advertisement writer, Macy's
1932 Published I Feel Better Now, Verses
1933 Published Out of My Head
1935 Published I Take It Back
1935 June 14 Married Alberto Gastone Antolini, chief rug buyer, Macy's
1937 Published One to a Customer: Collected Poems
1938 Published Safe Conduct: When to Behave--And Why
1940 Published Time for a Quick One
1940-1942 Copy Chief, Macy's
1942 Jan. 25 Son Anthony Frederick (Tony) Antolini born
1943-1947 Wrote Woman-Talk column in Liberty magazine
1945 Published Look Who's A Mother!
1948-1950 Copywriter, Cecil & Presbrey
1951 Copywriter, Warwick & Legler
1956 Divorced Alberto Antolini
1958 Copywriter, Young & Rubicam
1959 Oct. 1-1961 Copywriter, Doyle Dane Bernbach
1963 Published My Little Library: Dolls, Games, Rhymes
1963 Published Poems Made Up to Take Out
1968 Published The Animal Parade (translated from German)
1969 Published A Child's Book of Natural History
1985 Sept. 25 Died, Camden, Me.
Margaret Fishback Antolini was an advertising copywriter and author of light verse and prose. She was known for her wry, cynical attitudes towards domesticity, and her marriage to Alberto Gastone Antolini in 1935 prompted headlines such as Sneerer at Love Engaged to Wed ( The New York American, 17 April 1935). The couple had one son, Tony. Fishback lived in several New York City neighborhoods, settling in Murray Hill in 1941, where she would remain until at least 1976. She spent most summers in Thomaston, Maine.
Fishback contributed light verse and prose to a number of national publications, including Collier's, Cosmopolitan, Glamour, Good Housekeeping, Harper's Bazaar, Look, Mademoiselle, New York Times, Reader's Digest, Saturday Evening Post, and Woman's Day. She authored several compilations of light verse, an etiquette book called Safe Conduct: When to Behave--and Why, and two children's books. Common themes in Fishback's work include New York City, womanhood, marriage, and career. Fishback also frequently based her writings on stories and advertisements in newspapers. She published primarily under her maiden name, but also occasionally under her married name and the pseudonyms Marne and Marnie.
Fishback was described in a 1932 New York newspaper article as the highest-paid advertising woman in the world. In addition to her advertising work for Macy's and various advertising agencies, she also did extensive freelance work. Fishback contributed to advertising campaigns for Arrow Shirts, Borden's, Chef Boy-Ar-Dee, Clairol, DuPont, Gimbels, Great Atlantic & Pacific Tea Company (A&P), Hanes Hosiery, Martex, Norsk, Pabst Blue Ribbon, Seagram's, Simmons Beautyrest, and Wrigley, among several others. She was also a member of the professional society Advertising Women of New York (AWNY).
Biographical / Historical
Chronology of Major Published Work
1932 I Feel Better Now, Verses
1933 Out of My Head
1935 I Take It Back
1937 One to a Customer: Collected Poems
1938 Safe Conduct: When to Behave--And Why
1940 Time for a Quick One
1945 Look Who's A Mother!
1963 My Little Library: Dolls, Games, Rhymes
1963 Poems Made Up to Take Out
1968 The Animal Parade (translated from German)
1969 A Child's Book of Natural History
Collection Overview
The Margaret Fishback Papers span the years 1863 through 1978 and document Fishback's dual careers in advertising and writing as well as her personal life. The collection includes correspondence, layouts, drafts, galley proofs, radio scripts, working copy of advertising text, poetry, prose, published material, appointment books, scrapbooks, photographs, and other materials. Clients represented in the papers include Arrow, Borden's, Chef Boy-Ar-Dee, Clairol, General Foods, Gimbels, Gourmet Foods, Macy's, West Point Pepperell (Martex), Moore-McCormack Lines, Norcross, Norsk, Pabst, Simmons Beautyrest, and Wrigley. Materials that predate Fishback's birth consist of a small collection of 19th-century prints and illustrations.
The collection is organized into three series: Personal Files, Writings, and Advertising.
The Personal Files Series chiefly documents Fishback's personal life through personal correspondence, datebooks, diaries, and photographs. Also included are a number of items collected by Fishback such as etiquette books, newspaper clippings, church bulletins, and travel memorabilia. Biographical data, chiefly news articles, provide secondary source material about Fishback and her family.
The Writings Series documents Fishback's writing career, containing her published works as well as a large amount of work in unpublished form. Writings include articles and light poetry written for national news and general-interest publications such as Collier's, Liberty, Life, Look, the New York Times, New Yorker, Saturday Evening Post, and Time. Writings also include Fishback's contributions to women's magazines such as Cosmopolitan, Family Circle, Glamour, Good Housekeeping, Judge, Mademoiselle, McCall's, War Brides, Woman's Day, and Woman's Home Companion. A large number of Fishback's poems were reprinted as compilations; Fishback also compiled her own work in several scrapbooks. Materials represent Fishback's writings for children, including a promotional booklet for Martex and an English translation of a German poetry book. In addition to general prose and poetry, this series also includes materials collected and produced for a column entitled Woman-Talk, which Fishback wrote for Liberty from 1943 to 1947. Also included are short stories, greeting card work, letters to magazine and newspaper editors, speeches for various events such as author talks and advertising conventions, and other miscellaneous writings. General files document the administrative aspects of Fishback's writing career. These files contain correspondence, chiefly between Fishback and various editors and publishers, as well as financial and legal materials.
The Advertising Series documents Fishback's advertising work for R.H. Macy and Co. Department Store, as well as work for advertising agencies and freelance work. Included in this series are advertisements in various stages of production: notes, drafts, proofs, and tear sheets. Administrative materials, such as correspondence, often accompany the advertisements. Also represented in this series is evidence of Fishback's professional affiliations, particularly with the Advertising Women of New York (AWNY). Materials generated or collected in the process of preparing for speaking engagements with professional societies are also included. The series also includes a small collection of trade literature, chiefly books on advertising topics written by other authors.
Large-format print materials have been removed from their original series locations and relocated to Oversize Materials. Relocated items have been replaced in the Detailed Description of the Collection by dummy folders enclosed in brackets.
Related Materials
Materials related to this collection may be found in other Hartman Center collections, including the Nan Findlow Papers, Rena Bartos Papers, Lucile Turnbach Platt Papers, Sidney A. Olson Papers, David B. McCall Papers, and Garrett Orr Papers.
Separated Materials
A set of Fishback's published books, listed below, has been cataloged separately and is available in the Duke David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library. Individual titles can be found in the online library catalog. Duplicate copies of these books have remained with the collection.
I Feel Better Now, Verses (1932)
Out of My Head (1933)
I Take It Back (1935)
One to a Customer: Collected Poems (1937)
Safe Conduct: When to Behave--And Why (1938)
Time for a Quick One (1940)
Look Who's a Mother! (1945)
Poems Made Up to Take Out (1963)
The Animal Parade (1968)
New York (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 20th century; Women -- New York (State) -- New York; Appointment books; Clippings (information artifacts); Advertising copy; Advertising -- Social aspects; Advertising -- History -- 20th century; Women in advertising; Radio scripts; Scrapbooks; Scripts (documents); Layouts (printer matter); Photographs; Proofs (printed matter); Galley proofs; Women in the advertising industry -- New York (State); Tear sheets; Women authors; Women authors, American -- 20th century; Etiquette; Humor in advertising; Advertising executives; Advertising agencies; Advertising agencies -- New York (State) -- New York; Advertising agencies -- United States -- History; Wm. Wrigley Jr. Company; Young & Rubicam; Pabst Brewing Company; West Point Pepperell (Firm); Fishback, Margaret, 1904-1985; Borden Company; Advertising Women of New York; Chef Boy-Ar-Dee (Firm); Doyle Dane Bernbach Inc.; Clairol, inc.; General Foods Corporation; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; Gimbel Brothers; Moore-McCormack Lines, Inc.; Macy's (Firm)
- Personal Files Series, 1863-1976 and undated, 11 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  This series chiefly documents Fishback's personal life through personal correspondence, datebooks, diaries, and photographs. Also included are a number of items collected by Fishback such as etiquette books, newspaper clippings, church bulletins, and travel memorabilia. Biographical data, chiefly news articles, provide secondary source material about Fishback and her family. Materials that predate Fishback's birth consist of a small collection of 19th-century prints and illustrations.
  The series is arranged into six subseries--Biographical Data; Correspondence; Datebooks, Calendars, Diaries, and Address Books; Etiquette Materials; Photographs; and Other Papers--and alphabetically therein.
  Large-format materials have been removed to Oversize Materials. Where entire folders have been removed, their logical location in the container list has been indicated by dummy folders enclosed in brackets that indicate the physical location. Where single items have been removed, the relocation has been enumerated within parentheses.
  - Biographical Data Subseries, 1931-1970 and undated
    Materials, chiefly news clippings, providing biographical information about Margaret Fishback, husband Alberto Antolini, son Tony Antolini, and other family members. The bulk of the Fishback clippings pertain to her marriage to Antolini in 1935.
    - Margaret Fishback, 1931-1949 (Items removed to Oversize Materials, box OV1) (Box 1)
    - Margaret Fishback, 1951-1969 and undated (Box 1)
    - Other family members, 1941-1970 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence Subseries, 1918-1976 and undated
    Includes chiefly letters to and from friends and family members, who are often indicated by various nicknames. Son Tony is referred to as ZK, Tuck, and Tonino; husband Alberto as A.G.A. and Big Tony; brother Frederick Coleman (F.C.) Fishback as Comie; a male, older Antolini as Pie; among others. Fishback is often referred to as Nip by husband Alberto, Peg by son Tony, and Marnie by some friends.
    Other notable correspondents include author and playwright W. Somerset Maugham, with whom Fishback exchanged letters in 1961; illustrator Dick Sargent; author Frank Sullivan; actress Jane (Quigley) Alexander, who asked Margaret for writing advice as a child in 1949; elected officials, and various businesses.
    - 1918-1960, 9 folders, 1 item removed to Oversize Materials, box OV2 (Box 1)
    - 1961-1969, 9 folders (Box 2)
    - 1970-1976 and undated, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Datebooks, Calendars, Diaries, and Address Books Subseries, 1931-1974
    Datebooks and calendars frequently offer daily records of Fishback's activities. They are available for almost every year in the date range, with multiple datebooks or calendars in certain years. Diaries tend to also record daily activities without personal reflection.
    - Address books, 1937-1958, 11 folders (Box 3)
    - Address books, 1960-1967, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Datebooks and calendars, 1942-1955, 7 folders (Box 4)
    - Datebooks and calendars, 1956-1965, 10 folders (Box 5)
    - Datebooks and calendars, 1966-1970, 11 folders (Box 6)
    - Datebooks and calendars, 1971-1974, 9 folders (Box 7)
    - Desktop calendars, 1931-1949 (Box 8)
    - Diaries, 1935-1973, 8 folders (Box 9)
  - Etiquette Materials Subseries, 1933-1961 and undated
    Chiefly etiquette books and booklets collected by Fishback.
    - Advice to Young Ladies, 1933 (Box 9)
    - The Guest Is Always Right, 1944 (Box 9)
    - Hints on Etiquette, 1951 (Box 9)
    - I Didn't Do Anything, 1933 (Box 9)
    - Schedule: Everybody's Etiquette, 1949 (Box 10)
      A schedule of weekly presentations on various etiquette topics. Certain sessions have been highlighted in pencil by Fishback, including Don't Be a Dance-Floor Pirate, Is the Customer Always Right?, Advice to City Slickers, and Teen-Age Girls: How to Be Popular.
    - Slovenly Peter, or Cheerful Stories and Funny Pictures for Good Little Folks, undated (Box 10)
    - Tiffany's Table Manners for Teen-agers, 1961 (Box 10)
  - Photographs Subseries, 1942-1964 and undated
    Chiefly candid photographs dated 1942-1944 of Margaret with young son Tony in various New York locations including Central Park and East River, as well as at their home in Thomaston, Maine.
    - Family photographs, 1942-1944 (Box 10)
    - Other Photographs, 1950-1964 and undated (Box 10)
    - Photograph, 1930s (Box 39)
  - Other Papers Subseries, 1863-1973 and undated
    Miscellaneous personal items collected by Fishback.
    - Booklets, 1944-1945 (Box 10)
      Titles include: So You're Expecting a Bundle From Heaven! (1944), 9 of the World's Most Exciting Suspense Stories (1945), Is My Face Red!: Embarrassing Situations (1945), Happy Birthday!: Pin-up Birthday Record, Cartoons, Horoscopes, Fun Galore (1945), and With All My Love: 7 Tender Love Stories to Quicken the Beat of Your Heart (1945).
    - Chart, The Forms of Poetry, 1933 (Box 10)
    - Church materials, 1940-1973 and undated (Box 10)
      Materials chiefly document Fishback's involvement with the Episcopal Church of the Incarnation from 1954 to 1973, including her advertising work for the church's annual Christmas Fair. Also included is a confirmation certificate for Elizabeth Fishback, dated 1940. Church programs with extensive handwritten notes relating to Fishback's writings have been physically removed to the Other Writings Subseries of the Writings Series.
    - Clippings, 1909-1972 and undated
      - John F. Kennedy, Jr. assassination, 1963 (Box 10)
      - [ Portland Press Herald Victory Edition, 15 August 1945, removed to Oversize Materials, box OV1] (Box 10)
      - W. Somerset Maugham obituaries, 1965 (Box 10)
      - [W. Somerset Maugham poem, Looking Back Part II, Show, 1962, removed to Oversize Materials, box OV2] (Box 10)
      - 1909-1959, 3 folders (Box 10)
      - 1960-1972 and undated, 3 folders (Box 11)
    - Demorest's Family Magazine, 1890 (Box 11)
    - Directions to the Antolini residence, Cushing, Maine, undated (Box 11)
    - Engravings: paper dolls and cutouts, 1863-1868 and undated (Box 11)
      From an envelope titled Miss Elizabeth Fishback, many of these items are labeled with names of individuals, possibly members of the Fishback family.
    - Financial records, 1929-1955 (Box 11)
    - Goucher College Alumnae Association, 1964 and undated (Box 11)
    - Goucher College campaign bulletin, 1921 (Box 11)
    - Josephine Snapp Trophy application, 1938 (Box 39)
    - Notebook and personal notes, 1955? and undated (Box 11)
    - [ Organization Chart: Heaven, undated, removed to Oversize Materials, box OV2] (Box 11)
    - [ Papa Gander, publication of Woman's Home Companion, 1937, removed to Oversize Materials, box OV2] (Box 11)
    - Parent Teacher Association of Friends Seminary, 1949-1959 and undated (Box 11)
    - Personal scrapbook, 1911-1941 (Box 40)
    - Travel memorabilia, trip to Stanford, 1969 (Box 11)
    - Women's Press Club of New York City, literature program, 1967 (Box 11)
- Writings Series, 1926-1978 and undated, 17 boxes
  The materials in this series document Fishback's writing career, containing her published works as well as a large amount of work in unpublished form. Writings include articles and light poetry written for national news and general-interest publications such as Collier's, Liberty, Life, Look, the New York Times, New Yorker, Saturday Evening Post, and Time. Writings also include Fishback's contributions to women's magazines such as Cosmopolitan, Family Circle, Glamour, Good Housekeeping, Judge, Mademoiselle, McCall's, War Brides, Woman's Day, and Woman's Home Companion. A large number of Fishback's poems were reprinted as compilations; Fishback also compiled her own work in several scrapbooks. Materials also represent Fishback's writings for children, including a promotional booklet for Martex and an English translation of a German poetry book. In addition to general prose and poetry, this series also includes materials collected and produced for a column entitled Woman-Talk, which Fishback wrote for Liberty from 1943-1947. Also included are short stories, greeting card work, letters to magazine and newspaper editors, speeches for various events such as author talks and advertising conventions, and other miscellaneous writings.
  The series is arranged into seven subseries--General Files; Greeting Cards; Poetry; Prose; Scrapbooks; Speeches; and Other Writings--and alphabetically therein.
  General files document the administrative aspects of Fishback's writing career. These files contain correspondence, chiefly between Fishback and various editors and publishers, as well as financial and legal materials.
  A set of Fishback's published books has been cataloged separately and is available in the Duke Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library. Individual titles can be found in the online library catalog. Duplicate copies of these books have remained with the collection.
  - General Files Subseries, 1926-1973 and undated
    General files include materials documenting administrative aspects of Fishback's writing career.
    - Correspondence, 1926-1973 and undated
      Chiefly correspondence with magazine and newspaper publishers, these materials include a large amount of acceptance and rejection letters, materials related to copyright permissions, and some fan mail. Accompanying several letters is a wealth of Fishback's writing submissions, which have remained attached. Note that correspondence related to specific book projects has been filed under each book project in the Poetry Subseries.
      - General correspondence: 1926-1939, 9 folders (Box 12)
      - General correspondence: 1940-1954, 9 folders (Box 13)
      - General correspondence: 1955-1973 and undated, 8 folders; items removed to Oversize Materials, boxes OV2 and OV3 (Box 14)
      - Collins, Kenneth, 1961-1969 (Box 14)
        Fishback worked with Kenneth Collins at Macy's, where Collins worked from 1926-1932, becoming the executive vice president of the store in 1929. By the 1950s, he was a columnist for Women's Wear Daily, where he wrote the weekly column Today and Yesterday in Retailing. Collins frequently featured Fishback's poetry in the column. Correspondence between Fishback and Collins also includes clippings of the column and other related materials. Other Collins columns and correspondence can be found in the Scrapbooks Subseries, in the scrapbook titled M.F.A. scrapbook being worked on.
      - Williams, Gurney, 1943-1965 and undated, 3 folders (Box 14)
        Gurney Williams worked at Collier's before becoming the Humor Editor at Look magazine. Fishback was a frequent contributer to both magazines, particularly Look's Look on the Light Side feature. The correspondence chiefly pertains to Fishback's writing, but is occasionally more personal.
    - Financial and Legal Materials, 1929-1973 and undated
      Includes royalty and remittance statements, manuscript invoices, check stubs, and purchase agreements. Ledgers contain handwritten lists of compensation received for published writings.
      - General: 1929-1973 and undated, 7 folders (Box 15)
      - Ledgers: 1926-1932 and 1929-1933 (Box 15)
      - Ledgers: 1943-1950 and 1950-1958 (Box 15)
  - Greeting Cards Subseries, 1954-1968 and undated
    Includes poetry and prose for freelance greeting card projects.
    - American Artists Group, 1954-1955, 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Hallmark, 1962 (Box 16)
    - Norcross, 1968 (Box 16)
    - Other greeting card materials, undated (Box 16)
  - Poetry Subseries, 1926-1978 and undated
    Materials in this subseries include published and unpublished poems. Materials related to poetry compilations include book preparation materials, with clippings, correspondence, drafts, indices, notes, photographs, publicity materials, reviews, and tables of contents related to Fishback's published poetry compilations.
    This subseries also includes poems, published and unpublished, that appeared individually in magazines and newspapers. Many published versions of these poems were compiled as scrapbooks, and can be found in the Scrapbooks Subseries. Also included is a list, compiled by Fishback, of her published poems from 1926-1930.
    - Compilations, 1931-1968 and undated
      Includes book preparation materials, with clippings, notes, drafts, indices, tables of contents, correspondence, photographs, publicity materials, and reviews related to Fishback's published poetry compilations. A complete set of Fishback's published poetry compilations has been cataloged separately and is available in the Duke Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library. Individual compilations can be found in the online library catalog. Duplicate copies of these books have remained with the collection.
      Arrangement note
      Arranged alphabetically by compilation title.
      - The Animal Parade: Drafts and related materials, 1968 (Box 16)
      - I Feel Better Now, 1932 and undated
        - Book, 1932 (Box 16)
        - Review, Time, undated (Box 16)
        - Table of contents, undated (Box 16)
      - I Take It Back: Table of contents, 1935 (Box 16)
      - My Little Library series, 1963 (Box 16)
      - One to a Customer, 1937-1938 and undated